Guide to the Estela and Ernesto Bravo Film and Video Collection TAM.616
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series VI: The Cuban Excludables, 1989-1997; 477203
  - Salvador I Combinado, circa 1990s; cuid17883; 467644 (Box 18, Cassette ref409)
  - Combinado Guillermo Herera, circa 1990s; cuid17884; 467643 (Box 18, Cassette ref410)
  - "Excluibles vista al Combinados", circa 1990s; cuid17885; 467638 (Box 18, Cassette ref415)
  - Plane to Bus Arrival, 1991 December 12; cuid17886; 467637 (Box 18, Cassette ref416)
  - Flight 440 Interviews on bus, circa 1990s; cuid17887; 467636 (Box 18, Cassette ref417)
  - Guillermo " Mama balsero", 1991 September 19; cuid17888; 467635 (Box 18, Cassette ref418)
  - Flight Bus, 1991 December 19; cuid17889; 467634 (Box 18, Cassette ref419)
  - House of Julian Perez (Also on box "Ministry of the Interior" and "interesting observations"), 1992 January 30; cuid17890; 467632 (Box 18, Cassette ref421)
  - Interview Grandparents Guillermino, circa 1990s; cuid17891; 467573 (Box 19, Cassette ref480)
  - Interview with Guillermo and Juan Francisco, 1992 January 28; cuid17892; 467246 (Box 39, Cassette ref844)
  - "Excludables and rafts", circa 1990s; cuid17893; 467792 (Box 12, Cassette ref261)
  - Plane arriving (B-roll), circa 1990s; cuid17894; 467717 (Box 91, Cassette ref336, Box 80, Dvd ref336)
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:47:00.
  - Atlanta Stock (B-roll), circa 1990s; cuid17895; 479431 (Box 48, Cassette ref1092)
  - Atlanta Exterior (B-roll?), circa 1990s; cuid17896; 479442 (Box 49, Cassette ref1103)
  - Incidentals, cars, etc.(B-roll?), circa 1990s; cuid17897; 479487 (Box 61, Cassette ref1145)
  - Cuba, Birmingham Airport (B-roll?), circa 1990s; cuid17898; 479482 (Box 49, Cassette ref1140)
  - "Flight, plane...", 1991 December 19; cuid17899; 479465 (Box 64, Cassette ref1126)
  - Spanish annotations outside of box include "Experiments on the Cubans, corruption...", circa 1990s; cuid17900; 479484 (Box 49, Cassette ref1142)
  - "Demo 14 min Excludables", circa 1990s; cuid17901; 467415 (Box 33, Cassette ref638)
  - "The Excludables", circa 1990s; cuid17902; 467368 (Box 31, Cassette ref685)
- Series VII: Cubans in Peru, 1982; 479612
  This series contains a small amount of footage related to the documentary Cubans in Peru. The1982 film presents the experiences and views of some of the Cubans who took part in the occupation of the Peruvian Embassy in Havana in 1980. Videos from this documentary include footage of refugees in Tupac Amaru Stadium, interviews with Cuban political refugees, and footage of a Peruvian doctor who saved the life of a Cuban child. The scenes of the doctor and child are featured at the end of the documentary.
  - "Cubans in Peru DV#3", 1982; cuid785; 479613 (Box 55, Cassette ref1271)
    This video is 20 minutes in length, and most likely contains footage rather than the full-length documentary.
  - Cubans in Peru (has notes that say "Bad Copy" and "Dirty"), circa 1982; cuid17903; 479675 (Box 58, Cassette ref1332)
  - Children's Hospital and Tupac Amaru Park (B-roll), circa 1990; cuid17729; 479644 (Box 56, Cassette ref1301, Box 98, Dvd ref1301)
    This video features exterior footage of a children's hospital and Tupac Amaru Park in Lima, Peru. This video has no audio.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:06:23.
  - "Corvacho child Dr. Montano Peru", circa 1982; cuid17904; 479553 (Box 52, Cassette ref1211)
  - Peruvian Doctors: Interview about Cuban Child, circa 1982; cuid17905; 479564 (Box 53, Cassette ref1222, Box 98, Dvd ref1222)
    This video features an interview with two Peruvian doctors about a young Cuban boy in their care. They explain that the boy's mother had taken him from Cuba to Peru because she believed that he would get better medical care there. The doctors, however, explain that the boy has a complicated heart condition that they cannot treat. They discuss Peru's limited medical resources, and the need to send patients with more complicated medical issues to hospitals and clinics in Brazil. They explain they are only able to offer palliative care to the boy, and that he will need to go to another hospital for surgery.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:21:21.
  - Tupac Amaru Park: Footage, circa 1982; cuid786; 479657 (Box 59, Cassette ref1314, Box 96, Dvd ref1314)
    Tupac Amaru Park is a sports complex in East Lima that became a refugee camp for Cubans who were granted asylum in Peru after their 1980 occupation of the Peruvian Embassy in Havana.
    This video contains footage of Cuban exiles living in a tent city in Tupac Amaru Park in Lima, Peru. The video shows footage of concerned Peruvians speaking through a fence to the Cubans living in the park. It also includes some brief interviews with several Cubans living in the park about why they are there. Other footage features demonstrations and on-the-street interviews with Peruvians who oppose the presence of the Cuban exiles in the park as well as shots of local police in riot gear at the entrance to the park.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:22:31.
  - University of San Marcos: Presentation on Embajador En Cuba, circa 1982; cuid787; 467342 (Box 36, Cassette ref711, Box 95, Dvd ref711)
    This video begins with footage of a panel discussion at the University of San Marcos with scholars and diplomats discussing the relationship between Cuba and Peru, and the book Embajador en Cuba by Peruvian Ambassador Edgardo de Habich. At the end of the panel discussion Habich speaks briefly about his book before the footage ends. Microphones used during the panel create echo sounds in the auditorium, which make audio quality poor in various places. At minute 11:43 the footage changes to a brief interview with Habich in which he discusses the occupation of Tupac Amaru Park in Lima by Cuban Refugees, and the refugee status of the Cubans in the park.
    Original Format: Umatic. Duration: 00:20:13.
- Series VIII: Fidel: The Untold Story and Anecdotes about Fidel, 1995-2002; 477042
  The 2001 documentary Fidel: The Untold Story combines a history of the Cuban revolution with a more personal story of its leader, Fidel Castro. Because so much of the interview footage for Fidel: The Untold Story could not be included in the initial feature-length film, Estela and Ernesto Bravo made a follow-up documentary, Anecdotes about Fidel, in 2010. It includes portions of 24 interviews and expands on the stories about Fidel Castro.
  In 2001, Fidel: The Untold Story was selected for the Toronto Film Festival and won an award for "Distinguished Achievement for Excellence in Documentary Filmmaking" at the Urbanworld Film Festival in New York.
  This series contains clips, interviews, and background footage from the documentaries Fidel: The Untold Story and Anecdotes about Fidel. The 2001 documentary Fidel: The Untold Story combines a history of the Cuban revolution with a more personal story of leader, Fidel Castro. This series contains copies of both films. It includes complete interviews and portions of interviews highlighted in the two films. They feature historians, public figures, close friends, and Castro himself, and provide a glimpse into the life and personality of the Cuban leader. Interviewees include Alice Walker, Gabriel García Márquez, Arthur Schlesinger, Ramsey Clark, Ted Turner, Nelson Mandela, Charles Rangel, George McGovern, Philip Agee, and many others who share personal anecdotes along with political and historical perspectives.
  The anecdotes come not only from well-known Americans such as Harry Belafonte, Jesse Jackson, Angela Davis, Hank Aaron, Sydney Pollack and others, but also from many Cubans who are not well known in the United States. Among them are government officials and friends of Fidel such as Juan Almeida, Melba Hernández. Alfredo Guevara, Jorge Risquet, Antonio Núñez Jiménez, Alicia Alonso, Angela Castro, and Aleida Guevara.
  This series also contains a number of interviews that are not seen in the films. They include discussions with Hortensia Bussi de Allende, the widow of Salvador Allende, and American lawyer Victor Rabinowitz.
  Footage in this series also consists of clips from the Cuban State Council Archives and various news sources. Videos containing State Council footage often represent a wide date range. Some of the footage is dated 1998 which reflects the date the material was obtained, not the actual date of the events. The original dates of the footage were not recorded. Additional footage depicts Fidel Castro at a number of public events giving speeches or speaking with world leaders. Other materials in this series include documents related to the promotion and distribution of Fidel, including contact lists, posters, correspondence related to distribution rights.
  - Fidel: The Untold Story, 2000; cuid17906; 590451 (Reel ref1903_01, Reel ref1903_02, Reel ref1903_03, Reel ref1903_04, Reel ref1903_05, Reel ref1903_06, Reel ref1903_07, Reel ref1903_08, Reel ref1903_09, Reel ref1903_10, Reel ref1903_11, Reel ref1903_12, Reel ref1903_13, Reel ref1903_14, Reel ref1903_15, Reel ref1903_16, Reel ref1903_17, Reel ref1903_18)
    This is a full-length version of the film Fidel: The Untold Story. The complete documentary is contained on 6 positive film reels, 6 film negative reels, and 6 sound track reels.
  - "Fidel Trailer", circa 2000; cuid17907; 479388 (Box 47, Cassette ref1049)
  - Fidel - Logo Urbanworld, ver: 4.8, 2001 November 21; cuid17908; 593009 (Box 74, Disk ref2122)
  - An Evening with Estela Bravo: Filmmaker of "Fidel: The Untold Story" and "Anecdotes about Fidel" at the Paley Center for Media, New York City, 2012 May 9; cuid17909; 590464 (Box 73, Dvd 16)
    A film of the event honoring Estela Bravo, focusing on the release of Anecdotes about Fidel at the Paley Center for Media. Bravo speaks with Pat Mitchell about her life and career, and responds to questions from the audience. Clips are shown from Anecdotes about Fidel; There are also clips from other films that have dealt with Cuban-American relations, such as Miami-Havana, The Cuban Excludables, and Operation Peter Pan: Flying Back to Cuba.
  - Global Vision "Fidel Castro" FIX Optical Picture Negative, 2002 September 30; cuid17910; 593010 (Box 74, Reel 55)
  - Urban World - Logo - Project: Fidel Castro 35mm Negative, circa 2001; cuid17911; 593011 (Box 74, Reel 56)
  - Aaron, Hank: Interview, circa 1995-2000; cuid17912; 477048 (Box 68, Cassette ref846, Box 83, Dvd ref846)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:12:42.
  - Agee, Philip: Interview Transcript, undated; cuid17915; 590724 (Box 72, Folder 13)
  - de Allende, Hortensia Bussi: Interview, circa 1996; cuid17916; 467809 (Box 5, Cassette ref244, Box 77, Dvd ref244)
    - Agee, Philip: Interview Recording, 1997 March 8; cuid17913; 468038; 4 items This interview is contained on 4 access DVDs (Box 4, Cassette ref15, Box 75, Dvd ref15)
      Original Format: Betacam. Recording is divided into 4 access DVDs. Duration: Part 1 - 00:29:22; Part 2 - 00:08:00; Part 3 - 00:00:09; Part 4 - 00:01:25.
      In this interview Philip Agee begins by talking about his work for the CIA and the fallout after the publication of his book Inside the Company. He discusses his opinions about Fidel Castro and interest in Cuban life and culture. For the bulk of the interview he talks about United States policy toward Cuba and CIA efforts to overthrow Fidel Castro. He also touches on controversy surrounding the Kennedy assassination and discusses Americans' views about the Cuban revolution.
    - Agee, Philip: Interview Transcript, cuid17914; 593329
  - Alonso, Alicia: Interview (Cassette 1 1st Part), 1996 June 27; cuid17925; 477172 (Box 70, Cassette ref913, Box 85, Dvd ref913)
    Born Alicia Ernestina de la Caridad Martinez Hoya, Alicia Alonso (1921 - ) is a Cuban prima ballerina and choreographer. She and her husband lived in New York City for a time where she trained at the School of American Ballet. In 1959 they returned to Cuba. Fidel Castro invited her to head a new dance school (Ballet Nacional de Cuba).
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:28:36.
  - Aaron, Hank: Interview, circa 1995-2000; cuid291; 479247 (Box 45, Cassette ref983, Box 95, Dvd ref983)
    This video features an interview with baseball player Hank Aaron. At the beginning, Aaron briefly introduces himself and discusses his baseball career. The bulk of the interview focuses on Aaron's impression of Cuba and Fidel Castro. Aaron describes traveling to Cuba to film a documentary about Cuban baseball players, and describes the quality of education and baseball training he observed while in Cuba. He also discusses meeting Fidel Castro, and speaks specifically about Castro's athletic ability. Aaron also talks briefly about the poor diplomatic relations between Cuba and the United States, and argues that lack of trade and freedom of movement between the countries has contributed to the suffering of Cuban people and their family members in the United States.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:29:01.
  - Agee, Philip: Interview, 1997 March 8; 593328
  - Alarcón, Ricardo: Interview, 1998 November 21; cuid292; 479386 (Box 47, Cassette ref1047, Box 96, Dvd ref1047)
    Ricardo Alarcon de Quesada (1937 - ) is a Cuban statesman who served as Cuba's Permanent Representative to the United Nations for nearly 30 years. He was Cuba's Minister of Foreign Affairs from 1992-1993 and President of the National Assembly of People's Power from 1993-2013. During his time at the UN, Alarcon held several leading offices, such as Vice President of the General Assembly.
    This video features a portion of an interview with Ricardo Alarcón. At the beginning of the interview Alarcón discusses the political and diplomatic positions he has held within the Cuban government, including President of the National Assembly and United Nations ambassador. He discusses receiving the appointment of UN ambassador at the age of 28, and his inexperience in that position. He also describes meeting Fidel Castro for the first time when Castro's revolutionary forces entered Havana in January 1959. The bulk of the interview focuses on Alarcón's memories of Havana during the revolutionary period and the uncertainty during those years.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:27:08.
  - Alarcón, Ricardo: Interview, 1998; cuid293; 467846 (Box 10, Cassette ref207, Box 96, Dvd ref207)
    Ricardo Alarcón is a Cuban politician who served as Cuba's representative to the United Nations and President of Cuba's National Assembly.
    This video features a portion of an interview with Ricardo Alarcón. The recording does not start at the beginning and appears to only contain a portion of a larger interview. In this portion, Alarcón addresses Estela Bravo's questions about criticism of Cuba's lack of free press by comparing Cuba's press with privately owned newspapers in the United States. He criticizes the United States electoral system, which he contrasts with Cuban local elections. In the second half of the interview he talks about Cuba's role in Latin America, discussing both support for the Cuban government and opposition from what he describes as counter-revolutionary movements. He also talks about the significance of Fidel Castro's beard and his predictions for Cuba's future after Castro's presidency.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:31:51.
  - Alarcón, Ricardo: Interview, circa 1995-2000; cuid294; 467838 (Box 10, Cassette ref215, Box 96, Dvd ref215)
    This portion of an interview with Ricardo Alarcón begins with a discussion about Cuba in years before the overthrow of Fulgencio Batista's government. He discusses his memories of the revolution and the reaction of many Cubans to the revolution. He talks about the political trials following the revolution, and defends the actions of the new government. Estela Bravo asks Alarcón to describe what he views as the biggest successes and failures in the 40 years since the revolution, and Alarcón describes several domestic policies. They also discuss the ration booklets issued by the Cuban government, and Alarcón criticizes inequality in the United States.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:31:09.
  - Alarcón, Ricardo and Juanita Vera García, circa 1995-2000; cuid295; 479387 (Box 47, Cassette ref1048, Box 96, Dvd ref1048)
    This video features segments of two separate interviews. The first interview features Cuban politician Ricardo Alarcón. In this brief segment, Alarcón discusses Fidel Castro's personal appearance as a symbol of the revolution, the numerous assassination attempts made against Castro over the years, and the reasons many powerful people have expressed interest in meeting him. At minute 12:42 the footage changes to an interview with Castro's translator Juanita Vera García. García discusses how she became Castro's translator, and talks about what it is like to travel with Castro and act as interpreter for some of his long public speeches.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:28:09.
    - Almeida, Juan: Interview -1 Recording, 1997 June 5; cuid17917; 477150 (Box 69, Cassette ref893)
      Juan Almeida Bosque (1927-2009) was an important figure in the Cuban Revolution and later a Cuban official. He was the only Afro-Cuban to participate in the attack on the Moncada Barracks in 1953, and was also among the revolutionaries who participated in the 1956 Granma Yacht landing. He was later appointed the commander of the Third Front. During the US-sponsored Bay of Pigs operation in April 1961, Almeida commanded the Cuban military's Central Army. Later a prominent figure in the Communist Party of Cuba, Almeida was, at the time of his death, Vice-President of the Cuban Council of State and its third ranking member.
      This interview is in Spanish. Juan Almeida, who met Fidel Castro in 1952, shares personal stories about his relationship with Castro and talks about his earliest memories of the political situation in Cuba leading up to the revolution.
      Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:28:53.
    - Almeida, Juan: Interview -1 Transcript, 1997 June 5; cuid17918; 593332
  - Almeida, Juan: Interview -1, 1997 June 5; 593330
    - Almeida, Juan: Interview -2 Recording, 1997 June 5; cuid17919; 477151 (Box 69, Cassette ref894)
      In this part of the interview, Almeida discusses the Cuban revolution, including his memories of the Moncada attack and the Granma landing.
      Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:11:45.
    - Almeida, Juan: Interview -2 Transcript, 1997 June 5; cuid17920; 593371
  - Almeida, Juan: Interview -2, 1997 June 5; 593331
    - Almeida, Juan: Interview -3 Recording, 1997 June 5; cuid17921; 477152 (Box 69, Cassette ref895)
      In this portion of the interview Juan Almeida shares stories about Fidel's relationships with such figures as Che Guevara and Camilo Cienfuegos. He also provides other anecdotes and concludes with a discussion about his personal relationship with Fidel Castro.
      Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:33:22.
    - Almeida, Juan: Interview -3 Transcript, 1997 June 5; cuid17922; 593372
  - Almeida, Juan: Interview -3, 1997 June 5; 593333
    - Almeida, Juan: Interview -4 Recording, 1997 June 5; cuid17923; 477153 (Box 69, Cassette ref896)
      In this portion Juan Almeida talks about Fidel Castro as a symbol of the revolution, briefly discussing the significance of Castro's beard. He also talks about Castro's views of justice, his support of Angolan independence, and the anti-apartheid struggle in South Africa. He later discusses his feelings surrounding Castro's failing health.
      Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:04:56.
    - Almeida, Juan: Interview -4 Transcript, 1997 June 5; cuid17924; 593373
  - Almeida, Juan: Interview -4, 1997 June 5; 593334
  - Alonso, Alicia: Interview (Cassette 1 2nd Part), 1996 June 27; cuid17926; 477173 (Box 70, Cassette ref914, Box 85, Dvd ref914)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:03:09.
  - Alonso, Alicia: Interview (Cassette 2 1st Part) with Ramon Castro, 1996 June 27; cuid17927; 477174 (Box 70, Cassette ref915, Box 85, Dvd ref915)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:24:30.
  - Alonso, Alicia: Interview (Cassette 2 2nd Part) with Roman Castro, 1996; cuid17928; 479263 (Box 46, Cassette ref998)
  - Andreas, Duane: Interview, 1996 October 9; cuid17929; 479382 (Box 62, Cassette ref1043)
    Duane O. Andreas is a US business executive and former chairman and CEO of Archer Daniels Midland (ADM).
  - Aruca, Francisco: Interview, circa 1995-2000; cuid17930; 467835 (Box 5, Cassette ref218, Box 77, Dvd ref218)
    Francisco Gonzales Aruca (1941-2013) was a Cuban-American economist. He was a student at a Jesuit school in Havana at the time of the Cuban Revolution. He joined the counterrevolution and was arrested in 1961 by the Castro government. His political ideology later shifted in favor of the Cuban government, and he started the company Marazul Charters in New York with a goal of uniting fractured Cuban families.
    In this interview Francisco Aruca discusses people's polarized views of Fidel Castro. He discusses his own feelings about Castro, and spends some time talking about Castro's curiosity for politics. In the interview Estela Bravo asks Aruca about the slogan "No Castro, No Problem." Aruca talks about what he believes are problems with the sentiments behind the slogan, and suggests that in the present political climate, Cuba would be destabilized without Castro.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:21:46.
  - Aruca, Francisco: Interview, circa 1995-2000; cuid17931; 477142 (Box 69, Cassette ref885, Box 85, Dvd ref885)
    The initial 14 minutes feature footage of Aruca at work on the radio program Ayer en Miami. The remainder of the video is an interview of Aruca by Estela Bravo.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:29:00.
  - Aruca, Francisco: Interview, circa 1995-2000; cuid17932; 467983 (Box 3, Cassette ref70)
  - Aruca, Francisco: Footage at radio station, 1996 October 1; cuid17933; 477140 (Box 70, Cassette ref883, Box 84, Dvd ref883)
  - Aruca, Francisco: Footage, making telephone calls at radio station, 1996; cuid17934; 477141 (Box 70, Cassette ref884, Box 84, Dvd ref884)
  - Barnet, Miguel: Interview, circa 1995-2000; cuid17935; 477055 (Box 68, Cassette ref853, Box 84, Dvd ref853)
    Estela Bravo interviews Miguel Barnet, Cuban writer, novelist, and ethnographer. The interview is mostly in Spanish, but Estela Bravo speaks English at times.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:14:23.
  - Belafonte, Harry: Interview, 1996 August 12; cuid17936; 477059 (Box 68, Cassette ref857, Box 84, Dvd ref857)
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:10:48.
  - Belafonte, Harry: Interview, 1996 August 11; cuid17937; 477058 (Box 70, Cassette ref856, Box 85, Dvd ref856)
  - Benn, Tony: Interview (part 1), 1996 March 16; cuid17938; 467906 (Box 6, Cassette ref147, Box 77, Dvd ref147)
    Anthony Neil Wedgwood "Tony" Benn (1925 – 2014) was a British socialist and member of the Labour Party who served in House of Commons in the 1960s and 1970s. A leading member of Britain's anti-war movement, Benn opposed the isolation of Cuba and was an admirer of Fidel Castro.
    In the beginning of the interview Estela Bravo talks with Tony Benn about the initial reception of the documentary Fidel: The Untold Story, and the negative reaction Cubans in Miami had to the film. The official interview begins around minute 4:45. Benn begins by talking about his interest in watching the Cuban Revolution, and the impact it has had around the world in the years following. Much of the interview focuses on Benn's views about Fidel Castro and his leadership in Cuba.
    Original Format: Betacam. Duration: 00:28:59.
  - Benn, Tony: Interview (part 2), 1996 March; cuid17939; 468012 (Box 4, Cassette ref41, Box 75, Dvd ref41)